Alright, so after having a look at method overloading, which is the first way to implement
polymorphism in Java, which says one face many forms, now I want to talk about new addition
to the language.
Obviously, which is not relatively new now in 2026 was introduced a long way back, but
it's well worth talking about because it is a significant addition and we kind of use it
when it comes handy.
So if you have a look at this calculate or we're obviously overloading what purpose does
it serve is that we have multiple methods with the same name now, right?
But after a while you look at this situation and you still think that this is a bit repetitive,
right?
Because you're just multiplying two numbers, three and four numbers here.
And let's say they ask you that we don't know how many arguments would come in.
So you're going to just have different versions with multiply with five parameters, multiply
six, seven, let's say 20 parameters, 20 versions of multiply, but which is still never going
to be sufficed.
And it's never going to suffice the requirements because who knows their past 50 are humans
later on.
They want 15 numbers to be multiplied.
And that is where Java 5.0, which by the way is considered one of the greatest Java
versions ever released because of a number of significant features that were introduced
in this version.
And we talk about them and other features which were introduced in later versions as well.
But this particular one was exactly for this kind of a problem where we are not sure how
many arguments would be passed later on.
And when that is the requirement, then what you do is you try to convert the C, what
I do now is instead of having these three or seven 20 methods for multiply, which were
never going to be sufficient, I would just have one method.
And it will still work how that is variable arguments.
It was introduced in Java 5 in short, we call it where rocks and how does this work?
This works within at just one place in Java that is within parameters to a method right.
And that's why it's called variable arguments, the arguments which vary.
And for example, you have a method, for example, white and minty, this is where you define
it.
You say type any type of parameter that you're declaring.
And then you say I identified obviously like we have been doing until now, but after
Java 5, you do the three dots.
And that means now what happens is almost magically.
So white and minty can take now from zero to n arguments, right?
It can even take zero and it would work perfectly fine.
It can even take two, it can even take 50 and just one method for all kinds of situations.
And this in this case would be a drastic reduction of code, right?
So that is variable arguments following this syntax, let's compress our earlier program,
right?
Multiply, I'm not sure how many parameters would be passed, I'll just say in values and
put in see if I do it like this, it would exactly what one argument, but if I do something
like this, this is a catch also now, this is a take call scenario, it can take zero arguments,
works fine, it can take 75 arguments works perfectly fine.
And that is now it can take from zero to n number of integer values, absolutely wonderful.
Obviously, how would you write the code then the logic that depends on you because otherwise
you knew there were multiple methods and you just did multiply two numbers, three or
four, but how do you multiply here, right?
And that is using two new features of the language in Java 5, that is literally not new
as I said, but new at the time, but still significant, that is the enhanced for loop and variable
arguments.
See, I just took this internally behaves like an array, what else would it be, right?
So you say, for example, for, I'll say int value from values like we had earlier done,
and I'll say, I'll define one more variable, let me put it on local variable, I'll say
in total is equal to zero, and I will say, total multiply equal to the compound operator
remember, and then I'll say, so whatever is in this array, just multiply this and put
this result to total after the loop is done, I'll just say our start, I'll say, multiplication
of no matter how many numbers you put in, I'll just give you type of total, that's it.
Right, what is the warning?
What does it say?
It says that variable update does nothing, a redundant assignment, right?
So what we can do in status, you can also prefer writing it at the instance level, and
you don't need to instantiate it here, you know that, right?
Because instance variables like I told you in the previous videos, they have default values
in Java, and now this would just work.
So if you call multiply and you pass in three parameters works, if you call multiply
and without an argument still works, thanks to well, absolutely wonderful stuff this.
You pass in 20 arguments, works almost magically, and this was Java five variable arguments
and now on to the rules, how can you use it as I told you, the first rule is you can only
use it here, when you declare parameters to a method, right?
The second rule is a method can have only one where our parameter and the third rule is,
and that should be the last, again, a method can have only one variable argument parameter,
it should be the last, that is it can't be something like this, that's an error, but it
can be something like this.
Say perfectly fine because this is only one where our parameter in this method, and it's
the last parameter.
So now a question to you before I end this video, how many arguments are required at a
minimum to be passed to multiply, are there zero or something else?
Think about it before I see you in the next video.